<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-12-27T18:01:55+00:00</updated><id>https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Vikram Mahto | Mechanical Design Engineer</title><subtitle>Mechanical Design Engineer | Portfolio. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Getting Started with Creo Toolkit</title><link href="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/creo-toolkit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting Started with Creo Toolkit"/><published>2025-12-18T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-18T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/creo-toolkit</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/creo-toolkit/"><![CDATA[<p>As I write this post, I’m still learning Pro Toolkit. I’ve been exploring it for the last six months, and now I have a basic idea of how things work. You don’t have to be a programming geek to learn how to get things done using Pro/Toolkit, but a basic understanding of C/C++ is required to get started.</p> <h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>Creo Pro Toolkit is a powerful API that allows users to automate, customize, and extend the functionality of Creo Parametric. It provides a set of functions that enable developers to interact with Creo models, assemblies, and drawings programmatically. Many engineering companies use Pro Toolkit to improve design efficiency, reduce repetitive tasks, and create specialized applications tailored to their workflows.</p> <p>For someone starting out, Pro Toolkit may seem overwhelming at first, but once you get familiar with its structure and functions, it becomes much easier to work with. The key is to practice by working on small automation projects and gradually exploring more complex functionalities.</p> <h2 id="learning-resources">Learning Resources</h2> <p>If you’re interested in getting started with Creo Pro Toolkit, here are some useful resources:</p> <h3 id="1-ptc-documentation">1. PTC Documentation</h3> <p>The official PTC Creo Toolkit documentation is the best place to start. It provides detailed explanations of functions, data structures, and examples. You can find these files in your local installation:</p> <ul> <li><strong>ProToolkit User Guide (tkuse.pdf):</strong> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Creo Installation Directory\Common Files\protoolkit</code></li> <li><strong>API Wizard (Interactive Help):</strong> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Creo Installation Directory\Common Files\protoolkit\protkdoc</code></li> </ul> <h3 id="2-ptc-support--community">2. PTC Support &amp; Community</h3> <p>Platforms like the PTC Community and Stack Overflow have active discussions where developers share their experiences and solutions.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Useful Link:</strong> <a href="https://www.ptc.com/en/support/article/CS318242">PTC Support Article CS318242</a></li> </ul> <h3 id="3-sample-code-from-ptc">3. Sample Code from PTC</h3> <p>PTC provides example applications included with the Creo Toolkit installation. These are great for understanding basic implementations and syntax before writing your own code.</p> <h3 id="4-personal-experience--experimentation">4. Personal Experience &amp; Experimentation</h3> <p>The best way to learn is by working on real projects. Start by automating small tasks in Creo—like exporting parameters or automating model checks—and build your understanding step by step.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="automation"/><category term="creo"/><category term="automation"/><category term="coding"/><category term="c++"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A beginner's guide to navigating the PTC Creo Toolkit API, essential resources, and first steps in automation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Isn’t Austenitic Stainless Steel Magnetic?</title><link href="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/austenitic-steel/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Isn’t Austenitic Stainless Steel Magnetic?"/><published>2025-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/austenitic-steel</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/austenitic-steel/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>Steel is magnetic. Iron is magnetic. Nickel is magnetic. So why doesn’t your SS316 stainless steel stick to a magnet? This puzzle reveals how atomic structure, crystal arrangement, and alloy chemistry create materials with unexpected properties.</p> <h2 id="foundation-magnetism">Foundation: Magnetism</h2> <h3 id="the-atomic-origin">The Atomic Origin</h3> <p>Magnetism arises from unpaired electrons. When electrons pair up with opposite spins, their magnetic moments cancel. Unpaired electrons create a net magnetic moment turning each atom into a tiny magnet.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Ferromagnetism</strong> occurs when atomic magnetic moments spontaneously align in the same direction. Iron, nickel, and cobalt exhibit this through quantum mechanical exchange interactions, creating magnetic domains where billions of atoms align together. This produces strong macroscopic magnetism.</li> <li><strong>Paramagnetism</strong> involves unpaired electrons but lacks cooperative alignment. Atomic magnets remain randomly oriented. External magnets cause weak, temporary alignment hundreds of times weaker than ferromagnetism.</li> <li><strong>Diamagnetism</strong> occurs in materials with all paired electrons. External fields induce weak opposing currents, creating subtle repulsion.</li> </ul> <h2 id="foundation-crystal-structures">Foundation: Crystal Structures</h2> <h3 id="the-atomic-architecture">The Atomic Architecture</h3> <p>Crystal structure : how atoms arrange themselves , fundamentally affects material properties, including magnetism.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Body-Centered Cubic (BCC):</strong> Atoms at cube corners plus one at center. Each atom has eight nearest neighbors. Room-temperature iron (ferrite) has this structure. The specific atomic spacing creates optimal conditions for strong ferromagnetic exchange interactions.</li> <li><strong>Face-Centered Cubic (FCC):</strong> Atoms at cube corners plus one at each face center. Each atom has twelve nearest neighbors in dense packing. High-temperature iron (austenite) and many other metals adopt this structure.</li> </ul> <h3 id="the-critical-insight">The Critical Insight</h3> <p>The same element can be magnetic or non-magnetic depending on crystal structure.</p> <p>Iron demonstrates this perfectly:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Ferrite (BCC iron)</strong> at room temperature: strongly ferromagnetic</li> <li><strong>Austenite (FCC iron)</strong> above 912°C: weakly magnetic (paramagnetic)</li> </ul> <p>The iron atoms haven’t changed only their spatial arrangement. In BCC ferrite, atomic geometry favors parallel magnetic moment alignment. In FCC austenite, different atomic spacing weakens these interactions, preventing cooperative ferromagnetism.</p> <h2 id="the-iron-story-the-austenite-problem">The Iron Story: The Austenite Problem</h2> <h3 id="the-phase-diagram-puzzle">The Phase Diagram Puzzle</h3> <p>The iron-carbon phase diagram shows which crystal structures are stable at different temperatures. The critical feature: below 727°C, austenite (FCC) is thermodynamically unstable in plain carbon steel. It should transform to ferrite (BCC) and cementite (Fe₃C).</p> <p>Yet 304 and 316 stainless steels are austenitic (FCC structure) and used at room temperature far below 727°C. How can austenite exist where it shouldn’t?</p> <h2 id="the-stainless-steel-solution-alloying-creates-metastable-austenite">The Stainless Steel Solution: Alloying Creates Metastable Austenite</h2> <h3 id="nickel-the-austenite-stabilizer">Nickel: The Austenite Stabilizer</h3> <p>Nickel is an austenite-forming element that extends the temperature range where austenite is stable, pushing it downward. Nickel itself prefers FCC structure, so dissolved nickel atoms favor FCC arrangement in steel.</p> <p>For 18% chromium steel, approximately 8% nickel makes austenite stable (or metastable) at room temperature. This is why austenitic stainless steel is 18-8 composition.</p> <h3 id="chromium-the-dual-role">Chromium: The Dual Role</h3> <p>Chromium provides corrosion resistance through a protective oxide film. Additionally, when combined with nickel, chromium retards the kinetics of austenite-to-ferrite transformation dramatically slowing it down.</p> <p>Even if thermodynamics says austenite should transform, slow kinetics mean the transformation takes decades or longer. For practical purposes, austenite is stable.</p> <h2 id="the-non-magnetic-answer-why-austenitic-stainless-steel-isnt-magnetic">The Non-Magnetic Answer: Why Austenitic Stainless Steel Isn’t Magnetic</h2> <h3 id="the-mechanism">The Mechanism</h3> <p>When iron transforms from BCC ferrite to FCC austenite, magnetic properties change fundamentally. The FCC structure creates different atomic spacing and coordination that disrupts magnetic exchange interactions.</p> <p>In austenitic stainless steel, two factors eliminate ferromagnetism:</p> <ol> <li><strong>FCC Crystal Structure Effect:</strong> Different atomic geometry weakens the exchange interactions that promote magnetic moment alignment.</li> <li><strong>Alloying Complexity:</strong> Chromium and nickel create a heterogeneous atomic environment. Iron atoms are surrounded by a mixture of different elements rather than uniform iron. This disrupts the regular magnetic interactions needed for ferromagnetism.</li> </ol> <p>According to materials research, “the microstructure appears to be more random at the atomic layer, meaning that the electrons are unable to align their rotation in a consistent direction.” The complex atomic neighborhood prevents cooperative magnetic alignment.</p> <h3 id="why-magnetic-domains-dont-form">Why Magnetic Domains Don’t Form</h3> <p>Ferromagnetism requires magnetic domains regions where billions of atoms align their magnetic moments. In austenitic stainless steel, this cooperative alignment doesn’t occur. Atomic magnetic moments remain randomly oriented. The result is paramagnetism: weak, random atomic magnets producing negligible macroscopic magnetization.</p> <h2 id="critical-clarification-fcc--non-magnetic">Critical Clarification: FCC ≠ Non-Magnetic</h2> <p><strong>Important:</strong> FCC crystal structure does NOT automatically mean non-magnetic.</p> <ul> <li>Pure nickel has FCC structure and is strongly ferromagnetic</li> <li>Cobalt (at room temperature) has FCC structure and is ferromagnetic</li> </ul> <p>FCC structures can absolutely be magnetic. So why is austenitic stainless steel non-magnetic?</p> <p><strong>Answer:</strong> It’s the combination of FCC structure plus specific alloy chemistry (chromium, nickel, manganese) that disrupts magnetism. When iron transforms to FCC austenite in plain iron, it loses much ferromagnetism due to changed atomic spacing. But adding substantial chromium and nickel creates additional disruption beyond crystal structure alone.</p> <p>The heterogeneous atomic environment iron surrounded by different elements prevents the cooperative magnetic alignment that pure nickel achieves in its FCC structure.</p> <p>The lesson: Crystal structure influences magnetism, but electronic structure, alloying effects, and atomic environment all play critical roles. It’s not structure alone.</p> <h2 id="common-misconceptions">Common Misconceptions</h2> <p><strong>Myth 1: “Stainless steel isn’t magnetic.”</strong> <strong>Reality:</strong> Only austenitic stainless steel is non-magnetic (paramagnetic). Ferritic and martensitic grades are magnetic.</p> <p><strong>Myth 2: “If it’s magnetic, it’s not real stainless steel.”</strong> <strong>Reality:</strong> 430 ferritic stainless steel is genuinely stainless despite being magnetic. Grade choice depends on application requirements.</p> <p><strong>Myth 3: “Non-magnetic = better quality.”</strong> <strong>Reality:</strong> The correct grade for the application represents quality. Sometimes austenitic is ideal; sometimes ferritic is the sensible choice.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>Austenitic stainless steel’s non-magnetic nature isn’t a defect—it’s a consequence of its FCC crystal structure achieved through careful alloying. By adding nickel (austenite stabilizer) and chromium (corrosion resistance + kinetic retardation), materials scientists created an alloy where austenite exists indefinitely at room temperature as a metastable phase.</p> <p>The non-magnetic behavior results from:</p> <ul> <li>FCC structure’s effect on atomic spacing and magnetic exchange interactions</li> <li>Alloying-induced disruption of the atomic environment</li> <li>The combination preventing cooperative magnetic domain formation</li> </ul> <p>This same FCC structure also provides exceptional corrosion resistance and low-temperature toughness that make austenitic stainless steel indispensable in demanding applications.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="materials"/><category term="materials"/><category term="metallurgy"/><category term="stainless-steel"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This puzzle reveals how atomic structure, crystal arrangement, and alloy chemistry create materials with unexpected properties.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with plotly.js</title><link href="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2025/plotly/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with plotly.js"/><published>2025-03-26T14:24:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-26T14:24:00+00:00</updated><id>https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2025/plotly</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2025/plotly/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post with some <a href="https://plotly.com/javascript/">plotly</a> code.</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">plotly
</span><span class="sb">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [10, 15, 13, 17],
      "type": "scatter"
    },
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [16, 5, 11, 9],
      "type": "scatter"
    }
  ]
}</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Which generates:</p> <pre><code class="language-plotly">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [10, 15, 13, 17],
      "type": "scatter"
    },
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [16, 5, 11, 9],
      "type": "scatter"
    }
  ]
}
</code></pre> <p>Also another example chart.</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">plotly
</span><span class="sb">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [10, 15, 13, 17],
      "mode": "markers"
    },
    {
      "x": [2, 3, 4, 5],
      "y": [16, 5, 11, 9],
      "mode": "lines"
    },
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [12, 9, 15, 12],
      "mode": "lines+markers"
    }
  ],
  "layout": {
    "title": {
      "text": "Line and Scatter Plot"
    }
  }
}</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>This is how it looks like:</p> <pre><code class="language-plotly">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [10, 15, 13, 17],
      "mode": "markers"
    },
    {
      "x": [2, 3, 4, 5],
      "y": [16, 5, 11, 9],
      "mode": "lines"
    },
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [12, 9, 15, 12],
      "mode": "lines+markers"
    }
  ],
  "layout": {
    "title": {
      "text": "Line and Scatter Plot"
    }
  }
}
</code></pre>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="charts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included plotly.js code could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lifting Analysis of Transformer Tank Using Remote Points in ANSYS</title><link href="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/lifting-analysis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lifting Analysis of Transformer Tank Using Remote Points in ANSYS"/><published>2025-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/lifting-analysis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/lifting-analysis/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>Transformer tanks are critical components in electrical power systems, and their structural integrity during lifting operations is paramount for safety and reliability. During manufacturing, transportation, and installation, transformers must be lifted using designated lifting lugs or bollards. A proper lifting analysis ensures that these lifting points can safely support the transformer’s weight without excessive deformation or failure.</p> <p>In this blog post, we’ll explore how to perform a <strong>suspended condition lifting analysis</strong> of a transformer tank using <strong>ANSYS Mechanical</strong>, with a specific focus on the application of <strong>Remote Points</strong>—a powerful feature that simplifies constraint definition and accurately represents lifting cable connections.</p> <h2 id="what-is-lifting-analysis">What is Lifting Analysis?</h2> <p>Lifting analysis is a structural finite element analysis (FEA) performed to evaluate the stresses, strains, and deformations in a structure when it is suspended by lifting points. For transformer tanks, this analysis helps engineers:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Verify</strong> that lifting lugs can safely support the total weight.</li> <li><strong>Identify</strong> stress concentrations and potential failure points.</li> <li><strong>Ensure</strong> compliance with design codes and safety standards.</li> <li><strong>Optimize</strong> lifting lug design and placement.</li> <li><strong>Validate</strong> that deformations remain within acceptable limits.</li> </ul> <h2 id="understanding-suspended-condition-analysis">Understanding Suspended Condition Analysis</h2> <p>The analysis methodology presented here simulates the transformer tank in a <strong>suspended equilibrium condition</strong>—that is, when the tank is already lifted and hanging stationary from the lifting cables.</p> <p>This represents the state where:</p> <ul> <li>The tank is fully supported by lifting cables at designated lifting points.</li> <li>All forces are in equilibrium (no acceleration).</li> <li>The structure experiences maximum sustained loading.</li> <li>Cable tensions equal the distributed weight of the transformer.</li> </ul> <p>This approach is widely used in industry as it provides a clear, direct assessment of structural stresses while the transformer hangs suspended during transportation or installation.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/lifting-analysis/01-suspended-equilibrium.jpg" alt="Suspended equilibrium condition of Transformer cover"/> <em>Figure 1: Suspended equilibrium condition diagram.</em></p> <h2 id="why-use-remote-points">Why Use Remote Points?</h2> <p>Remote points in ANSYS are powerful tools that allow you to apply constraints at a reference location that is connected to a set of nodes or surfaces through kinematic coupling equations. They are special nodes in the model that represent a collection of points or a portion of the structure, helping to simplify complex behaviors by reducing multiple degrees of freedom to fewer, manageable ones.</p> <h3 id="how-remote-points-work">How Remote Points Work</h3> <p>Remote points function through <strong>Multi-Point Constraint (MPC)</strong> equations that manage the relationship between independent and dependent degrees of freedom:</p> <ul> <li>The <strong>remote point</strong> acts as an independent node in space coordinates.</li> <li>The <strong>scoped geometry</strong> (lifting hole surface) contains dependent nodes.</li> <li><strong>MPC equations</strong> link these together, transferring constraints from the remote point to the geometry.</li> <li>Dependent degrees of freedom are eliminated from the system, simplifying the solution process.</li> </ul> <p>This mechanism ensures that constraints applied remotely are correctly transferred to the actual model geometry while maintaining physical accuracy.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="methodology">Methodology</h2> <h3 id="1-geometry-preparation">1. Geometry Preparation</h3> <p>Start with a 3D CAD model of your transformer tank. The model used in this analysis was created in Creo and imported into ANSYS.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/lifting-analysis/02-cleaned-geometry.jpg" alt="Cleaned geometry"/> <em>Figure 2: Cleaned CAD geometry ready for analysis.</em></p> <p><strong>Essential components to include:</strong></p> <ul> <li>Main tank body (shell)</li> <li>Lifting lugs with mounting pads</li> <li>Major structural reinforcements</li> <li>Base plate or support structure</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p><strong>Note:</strong> Remove small features like bolt holes if they’re far from critical regions. Keep the lifting lug geometry detailed as it’s the region of interest.</p> </blockquote> <h3 id="2-material-definition">2. Material Definition</h3> <p>Define material properties in ANSYS Engineering Data.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Material:</strong> Structural Steel (typical for transformer tanks)</li> <li><strong>Young’s Modulus:</strong> 200 GPa</li> <li><strong>Poisson’s Ratio:</strong> 0.3</li> <li><strong>Density:</strong> 7850 kg/m³</li> <li><strong>Yield Strength:</strong> 250 MPa</li> </ul> <h3 id="3-contact-definitions">3. Contact Definitions</h3> <p>For multi-body assemblies, create appropriate contacts between components.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Contact Type:</strong> Bonded (This simulates a welded connection).</li> </ul> <h3 id="4-meshing-strategy">4. Meshing Strategy</h3> <p>A proper mesh is crucial for accurate results at the lifting points.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Lifting lug region:</strong> Element size: 2-5 mm (fine mesh). Use the “Sphere of influence” method around lifting holes.</li> <li><strong>Tank body:</strong> Element size: 20 mm.</li> </ul> <h3 id="5-creating-coordinate-systems">5. Creating Coordinate Systems</h3> <p>Create coordinate systems at the <strong>lifting hook position</strong>. This is the point where the lifting cables (slings) converge and connect to the crane hook.</p> <p><strong>Understanding Sling Geometry:</strong> In practical lifting operations, multiple slings connect the lifting lugs to a common lifting hook above. The geometry involves:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Slinging angle:</strong> The angle between the sling and the vertical axis (typically 60° as per standard practice).</li> <li><strong>Lifting angle:</strong> The angle at the hook where slings converge.</li> <li><strong>Hook height:</strong> Vertical distance from lifting lug to the hook convergence point.</li> </ul> <p><img src="/assets/img/lifting-analysis/03-cbip-sling-geometry.jpg" alt="CBIP Manual Section CC Sling Geometry"/> <em>Figure 3: Sling geometry reference (CBIP Manual: Section CC).</em></p> <p><strong>Steps to create Coordinate System:</strong></p> <ol> <li>Select the internal surface of the lifting lug/eye or surface of the lifting bollard.</li> <li>Insert → Coordinate System.</li> <li>This will create a Coordinate System at the centroid of the lifting lugs (x,z).</li> <li>Add a <strong>vertical offset</strong> for the location of the Lifting hook (y). <em>(If hook height is unknown: Calculate it from sling length and angle).</em></li> </ol> <p><img src="/assets/img/lifting-analysis/04-csys-created.jpg" alt="Coordinate System Created at Hook Location"/> <em>Figure 4: Coordinate System created at the theoretical hook convergence point.</em></p> <h3 id="6-creating-remote-points---the-key-step">6. Creating Remote Points - The Key Step</h3> <p><strong>Step 1: Insert Remote Point</strong> Right-click on Model → Insert → Remote Point.</p> <p><strong>Step 2: Define Scoping</strong> Configure the remote point settings as follows:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Scoping Method:</strong> Geometry Selection.</li> <li><strong>Geometry:</strong> Select the inner cylindrical surface of all lifting holes (can select multiple faces for all lugs).</li> <li><strong>Coordinate System:</strong> Select the coordinate system created in Step 5 (at hook position). <em>(Coordinates will automatically populate X, Y, Z = 0 mm relative to selected coordinate system).</em></li> </ul> <p><img src="/assets/img/lifting-analysis/05-remote-point-setup.jpg" alt="Remote Point Scoping in ANSYS"/> <em>Figure 5: Defining the Remote Point in ANSYS.</em></p> <h3 id="7-applying-loads">7. Applying Loads</h3> <p>The suspended condition analysis requires applying all downward forces that the lifting system must support.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Load:</strong> Standard Earth Gravity</li> <li><strong>Application:</strong> Insert → Standard Earth Gravity</li> <li><strong>Direction:</strong> Negative Y-axis (or Z-axis, depending on your coordinate system)</li> <li><strong>Magnitude:</strong> 9.81 m/s² (automatically applied)</li> </ul> <p><strong>What this does:</strong> It applies gravitational acceleration to all bodies. The weight is calculated automatically (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Force = Mass × 9.81</code>), where Mass comes from <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Volume × Density</code>.</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Note:</strong> This blog focuses on empty tank lifting, so we only use Standard Earth Gravity. Additional loads of Oil and Active Part can be applied on the base plate if required.</p> </blockquote> <h3 id="8-applying-boundary-conditions">8. Applying Boundary Conditions</h3> <p>At the remote point, we need to simulate the hook holding the system stationary.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Insert → Remote Displacement</strong></li> <li>Set <strong>ALL</strong> degrees of freedom to <strong>ZERO</strong>: <ul> <li>X Displacement: 0</li> <li>Y Displacement: 0</li> <li>Z Displacement: 0</li> <li>X Rotation: 0</li> <li>Y Rotation: 0</li> <li>Z Rotation: 0</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>The remote points represent lifting cable attachment points. Setting DOF = 0 means these points are held stationary in space, supporting the tank.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="solution-and-results">Solution and Results</h2> <p>Insert the following result items to evaluate the analysis:</p> <h3 id="stress-results">Stress Results</h3> <p><strong>Equivalent (von Mises) Stress:</strong> This is the most commonly used failure criterion for ductile materials.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/lifting-analysis/06-stress-result.jpg" alt="Equivalent Von Mises Stress Result"/> <em>Figure 6: Equivalent (von Mises) Stress distribution.</em></p> <h3 id="deformation-results">Deformation Results</h3> <p><strong>Total Deformation:</strong> Check the overall displacement of the structure.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/lifting-analysis/07-deformation-result.jpg" alt="Total Deformation Result (scaled)"/> <em>Figure 7: Total Deformation (200% scaled visualization).</em></p> <h3 id="reaction-forces-validation">Reaction Forces (Validation)</h3> <p>This is a critical step to validate your setup. Insert a <strong>Force Reaction</strong> probe at each remote point.</p> <ul> <li>This displays reaction forces in X, Y, and Z directions.</li> <li>The <strong>Y component (vertical)</strong> represents the cable tension.</li> <li>The sum of all vertical reactions should equal the total weight of the model.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Validation Check:</strong></p> <p>First, verify the total mass of your geometry from the properties menu: <img src="/assets/img/lifting-analysis/08-geometry-properties.jpg" alt="Geometry Properties showing Mass"/> <em>Figure 8: Checking total mass in geometry properties.</em></p> <p>Next, check the resultant force from the reaction probes: <img src="/assets/img/lifting-analysis/09-reaction-forces.jpg" alt="Reaction Force Probe Results"/> <em>Figure 9: Reaction forces at the lifting points.</em></p> <p><strong>Calculation:</strong></p> <ul> <li>Total weight = $13610 \text{ kg} \times 9.81 \text{ m/s}^2 = 133,514 \text{ N}$</li> <li>Reactions in Y (from ANSYS) = <strong>133,460 N</strong></li> </ul> <p>Since $133,514 \text{ N} \approx 133,460 \text{ N}$, the force balance confirms that the model is in equilibrium, the setup is correct, and the results are valid.</p> <h2 id="what-do-the-standards-say">What Do the Standards Say?</h2> <p>Ensure your design complies with relevant local and international standards.</p> <p><strong>CBIP (Central Board of Irrigation and Power)</strong> <img src="/assets/img/lifting-analysis/10-cbip-standard.jpg" alt="CBIP Standard Reference"/></p> <p><strong>CEA (Central Electricity Authority)</strong> <img src="/assets/img/lifting-analysis/11-cea-standard.jpg" alt="CEA Standard Reference"/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="engineering"/><category term="ansys"/><category term="fea"/><category term="engineering"/><category term="transformers"/><category term="lifting"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A detailed guide on simulating suspended lifting scenarios for heavy transformer tanks using ANSYS Mechanical and Remote Points.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with image galleries</title><link href="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/photo-gallery/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with image galleries"/><published>2024-12-04T01:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-04T01:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/photo-gallery</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/photo-gallery/"><![CDATA[<p>The images in this post are all zoomable, arranged into different mini-galleries using different libraries.</p> <h2 id="lightbox2"><a href="https://lokeshdhakar.com/projects/lightbox2/">Lightbox2</a></h2> <p><a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-2500.jpg" data-lightbox="roadtrip"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-200.jpg"/></a> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-2500.jpg" data-lightbox="roadtrip"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-200.jpg"/></a> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-2500.jpg" data-lightbox="roadtrip"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-200.jpg"/></a></p> <hr/> <h2 id="photoswipe"><a href="https://photoswipe.com/">PhotoSwipe</a></h2> <div class="pswp-gallery pswp-gallery--single-column" id="gallery--getting-started"> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-2500.jpg" data-pswp-width="1669" data-pswp-height="2500" target="_blank"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-200.jpg" alt=""/> </a> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/7/img-2500.jpg" data-pswp-width="1875" data-pswp-height="2500" data-cropped="true" target="_blank"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/7/img-200.jpg" alt=""/> </a> <a href="https://unsplash.com" data-pswp-src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-2500.jpg" data-pswp-width="2500" data-pswp-height="1666" target="_blank"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-200.jpg" alt=""/> </a> <div> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/6/img-2500.jpg" data-pswp-width="2500" data-pswp-height="1667" target="_blank"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/6/img-200.jpg" alt=""/> </a> </div> </div> <hr/> <h2 id="spotlight-js"><a href="https://nextapps-de.github.io/spotlight/">Spotlight JS</a></h2> <div class="spotlight-group"> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-200.jpg"/> </a> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-200.jpg"/> </a> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-200.jpg"/> </a> </div> <div class="spotlight-group"> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/4/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/4/img-200.jpg"/> </a> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/5/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/5/img-200.jpg"/> </a> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/6/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/6/img-200.jpg"/> </a> </div> <hr/> <h2 id="venobox"><a href="https://veno.es/venobox/">Venobox</a></h2> <p><a class="venobox" data-gall="myGallery" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-2500.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-200.jpg"/></a> <a class="venobox" data-gall="myGallery" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-2500.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-200.jpg"/></a> <a class="venobox" data-gall="myGallery" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-2500.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-200.jpg"/></a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="images"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included image galleries could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra</title><link href="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra"/><published>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/"><![CDATA[<p>May 14, 2024 We’re introducing a series of updates across the Gemini family of models, including the new 1.5 Flash, our lightweight model for speed and efficiency, and Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants. In December, we launched our first natively multimodal model Gemini 1.0 in three sizes: Ultra, Pro and Nano. Just a few months later we released 1.5 Pro, with enhanced performance and a breakthrough long context window of 1 million tokens.Developers and enterprise customers have been putting 1.5 Pro to use in incredible ways and finding its long context window, multimodal reasoning capabilities and impressive overall performance incredibly useful.We know from user feedback that some applications need lower latency and a lower cost to serve. This inspired us to keep innovating, so today, we’re introducing Gemini 1.5 Flash: a model that’s lighter-weight than 1.5 Pro, and designed to be fast and efficient to serve at scale.Both 1.5 Pro and 1.5 Flash are available in public preview with a 1 million token context window in Google AI Studio and Vertex AI. And now, 1.5 Pro is also available with a 2 million token context window via waitlist to developers using the API and to Google Cloud customers.We’re also introducing updates across the Gemini family of models, announcing our next generation of open models, Gemma 2, and sharing progress on the future of AI assistants, with Project Astra.Context lengths of leading foundation models compared with Gemini 1.5’s 2 million token capability1.5 Flash is the newest addition to the Gemini model family and the fastest Gemini model served in the API. It’s optimized for high-volume, high-frequency tasks at scale, is more cost-efficient to serve and features our breakthrough long context window.While it’s a lighter weight model than 1.5 Pro, it’s highly capable of multimodal reasoning across vast amounts of information and delivers impressive quality for its size.The new Gemini 1.5 Flash model is optimized for speed and efficiency, is highly capable of multimodal reasoning and features our breakthrough long context window.1.5 Flash excels at summarization, chat applications, image and video captioning, data extraction from long documents and tables, and more. This is because it’s been trained by 1.5 Pro through a process called “distillation,” where the most essential knowledge and skills from a larger model are transferred to a smaller, more efficient model.Read more about 1.5 Flash in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report, on the Gemini technology page, and learn about 1.5 Flash’s availability and pricing.Over the last few months, we’ve significantly improved 1.5 Pro, our best model for general performance across a wide range of tasks.Beyond extending its context window to 2 million tokens, we’ve enhanced its code generation, logical reasoning and planning, multi-turn conversation, and audio and image understanding through data and algorithmic advances. We see strong improvements on public and internal benchmarks for each of these tasks.1.5 Pro can now follow increasingly complex and nuanced instructions, including ones that specify product-level behavior involving role, format and style. We’ve improved control over the model’s responses for specific use cases, like crafting the persona and response style of a chat agent or automating workflows through multiple function calls. And we’ve enabled users to steer model behavior by setting system instructions.We added audio understanding in the Gemini API and Google AI Studio, so 1.5 Pro can now reason across image and audio for videos uploaded in Google AI Studio. And we’re now integrating 1.5 Pro into Google products, including Gemini Advanced and in Workspace apps.Read more about 1.5 Pro in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report and on the Gemini technology page.Gemini Nano is expanding beyond text-only inputs to include images as well. Starting with Pixel, applications using Gemini Nano with Multimodality will be able to understand the world the way people do — not just through text, but also through sight, sound and spoken language.Read more about Gemini 1.0 Nano on Android.Today, we’re also sharing a series of updates to Gemma, our family of open models built from the same research and technology used to create the Gemini models.We’re announcing Gemma 2, our next generation of open models for responsible AI innovation. Gemma 2 has a new architecture designed for breakthrough performance and efficiency, and will be available in new sizes.The Gemma family is also expanding with PaliGemma, our first vision-language model inspired by PaLI-3. And we’ve upgraded our Responsible Generative AI Toolkit with LLM Comparator for evaluating the quality of model responses.Read more on the Developer blog.As part of Google DeepMind’s mission to build AI responsibly to benefit humanity, we’ve always wanted to develop universal AI agents that can be helpful in everyday life. That’s why today, we’re sharing our progress in building the future of AI assistants with Project Astra (advanced seeing and talking responsive agent).To be truly useful, an agent needs to understand and respond to the complex and dynamic world just like people do — and take in and remember what it sees and hears to understand context and take action. It also needs to be proactive, teachable and personal, so users can talk to it naturally and without lag or delay.While we’ve made incredible progress developing AI systems that can understand multimodal information, getting response time down to something conversational is a difficult engineering challenge. Over the past few years, we’ve been working to improve how our models perceive, reason and converse to make the pace and quality of interaction feel more natural.Building on Gemini, we’ve developed prototype agents that can process information faster by continuously encoding video frames, combining the video and speech input into a timeline of events, and caching this information for efficient recall.By leveraging our leading speech models, we also enhanced how they sound, giving the agents a wider range of intonations. These agents can better understand the context they’re being used in, and respond quickly, in conversation.With technology like this, it’s easy to envision a future where people could have an expert AI assistant by their side, through a phone or glasses. And some of these capabilities are coming to Google products, like the Gemini app and web experience, later this year.We’ve made incredible progress so far with our family of Gemini models, and we’re always striving to advance the state-of-the-art even further. By investing in a relentless production line of innovation, we’re able to explore new ideas at the frontier, while also unlocking the possibility of new and exciting Gemini use cases.Learn more about Gemini and its capabilities. Your information will be used in accordance with Google’s privacy policy.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>      Done. Just one step more.
    
      Check your inbox to confirm your subscription.
    You are already subscribed to our newsletter.
    You can also subscribe with a
    different email address
    
    .
    
  Let’s stay in touch. Get the latest news from Google in your inbox.
          Follow Us
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re sharing updates across our Gemini family of models and a glimpse of Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with tabs</title><link href="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/tabs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with tabs"/><published>2024-05-01T00:32:13+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-01T00:32:13+00:00</updated><id>https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/tabs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/tabs/"><![CDATA[<p>This is how a post with <a href="https://github.com/Ovski4/jekyll-tabs">tabs</a> looks like. Note that the tabs could be used for different purposes, not only for code.</p> <h2 id="first-tabs">First tabs</h2> <p>To add tabs, use the following syntax:</p> <div class="language-liquid highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">tabs</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">group-name</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>

<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">tab</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">group-name</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">tab-name-1</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>

Content 1

<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endtab</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>

<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">tab</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">group-name</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">tab-name-2</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>

Content 2

<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endtab</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>

<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endtabs</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>With this you can generate visualizations like:</p> <ul id="log" class="tab" data-tab="d1eecdda-1513-4307-9de2-f9bad84d9eef" data-name="log"> <li class="active" id="log-php"> <a href="#">php </a> </li> <li id="log-js"> <a href="#">js </a> </li> <li id="log-ruby"> <a href="#">ruby </a> </li> </ul> <ul class="tab-content" id="d1eecdda-1513-4307-9de2-f9bad84d9eef" data-name="log"> <li class="active"> <div class="language-php highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">var_dump</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'hello'</span><span class="p">);</span>
</code></pre></div></div> </li> <li> <div class="language-javascript highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nx">console</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">log</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2">hello</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="p">);</span>
</code></pre></div></div> </li> <li> <div class="language-javascript highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nx">pputs</span> <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">hello</span><span class="dl">'</span>
</code></pre></div></div> </li> </ul> <h2 id="another-example">Another example</h2> <ul id="data-struct" class="tab" data-tab="28bc50fa-ba62-4521-a9bf-7afe33b6ca12" data-name="data-struct"> <li class="active" id="data-struct-yaml"> <a href="#">yaml </a> </li> <li id="data-struct-json"> <a href="#">json </a> </li> </ul> <ul class="tab-content" id="28bc50fa-ba62-4521-a9bf-7afe33b6ca12" data-name="data-struct"> <li class="active"> <div class="language-yaml highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="na">hello</span><span class="pi">:</span>
  <span class="pi">-</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="s">whatsup"</span>
  <span class="pi">-</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="s">hi"</span>
</code></pre></div></div> </li> <li> <div class="language-json highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
  </span><span class="nl">"hello"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="s2">"whatsup"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"hi"</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="p">}</span><span class="w">
</span></code></pre></div></div> </li> </ul> <h2 id="tabs-for-something-else">Tabs for something else</h2> <ul id="something-else" class="tab" data-tab="76db6995-6da2-4c56-ac49-7201446883a7" data-name="something-else"> <li class="active" id="something-else-text"> <a href="#">text </a> </li> <li id="something-else-quote"> <a href="#">quote </a> </li> <li id="something-else-list"> <a href="#">list </a> </li> </ul> <ul class="tab-content" id="76db6995-6da2-4c56-ac49-7201446883a7" data-name="something-else"> <li class="active"> <p>Regular text</p> </li> <li> <blockquote> <p>A quote</p> </blockquote> </li> <li> <p>Hipster list</p> <ul> <li>brunch</li> <li>fixie</li> <li>raybans</li> <li>messenger bag</li> </ul> </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included tabs in a post could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with typograms</title><link href="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/typograms/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with typograms"/><published>2024-04-29T23:36:10+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-29T23:36:10+00:00</updated><id>https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/typograms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/typograms/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post with some <a href="https://github.com/google/typograms/">typograms</a> code.</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">typograms
</span><span class="sb">+----+
|    |---&gt; My first diagram!
+----+</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Which generates:</p> <pre><code class="language-typograms">+----+
|    |---&gt; My first diagram!
+----+
</code></pre> <p>Another example:</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">typograms
</span><span class="sb">.------------------------.
|.----------------------.|
||"https://example.com" ||
|'----------------------'|
| ______________________ |
||                      ||
||   Welcome!           ||
||                      ||
||                      ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  | username       |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  |"*******"       |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||                      ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  |   "Sign-up"    |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||                      ||
|+----------------------+|
.------------------------.</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>which generates:</p> <pre><code class="language-typograms">.------------------------.
|.----------------------.|
||"https://example.com" ||
|'----------------------'|
| ______________________ |
||                      ||
||   Welcome!           ||
||                      ||
||                      ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  | username       |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  |"*******"       |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||                      ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  |   "Sign-up"    |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||                      ||
|+----------------------+|
.------------------------.
</code></pre> <p>For more examples, check out the <a href="https://google.github.io/typograms/#examples">typograms documentation</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="diagrams"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included typograms code could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post that can be cited</title><link href="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/post-citation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post that can be cited"/><published>2024-04-28T15:06:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-28T15:06:00+00:00</updated><id>https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/post-citation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/post-citation/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post that can be cited. The content of the post ends here, while the citation information is automatically provided below. The only thing needed is for you to set the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">citation</code> key in the front matter to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">true</code>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="citation"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what a post that can be cited looks like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with pseudo code</title><link href="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/pseudocode/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with pseudo code"/><published>2024-04-15T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-15T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/pseudocode</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vikrammahtodesign.github.io/blog/2024/pseudocode/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post with some pseudo code rendered by <a href="https://github.com/SaswatPadhi/pseudocode.js">pseudocode</a>. The example presented here is the same as the one in the <a href="https://saswat.padhi.me/pseudocode.js/">pseudocode.js</a> documentation, with only one simple but important change: everytime you would use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$</code>, you should use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$$</code> instead. Also, note that the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pseudocode</code> key in the front matter is set to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">true</code> to enable the rendering of pseudo code. As an example, using this code:</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">pseudocode
</span><span class="sb">% This quicksort algorithm is extracted from Chapter 7, Introduction to Algorithms (3rd edition)
\begin{algorithm}
\caption{Quicksort}
\begin{algorithmic}
\PROCEDURE{Quicksort}{$$A, p, r$$}
    \IF{$$p &lt; r$$}
        \STATE $$q = $$ \CALL{Partition}{$$A, p, r$$}
        \STATE \CALL{Quicksort}{$$A, p, q - 1$$}
        \STATE \CALL{Quicksort}{$$A, q + 1, r$$}
    \ENDIF
\ENDPROCEDURE
\PROCEDURE{Partition}{$$A, p, r$$}
    \STATE $$x = A[r]$$
    \STATE $$i = p - 1$$
    \FOR{$$j = p$$ \TO $$r - 1$$}
        \IF{$$A[j] &lt; x$$}
            \STATE $$i = i + 1$$
            \STATE exchange
            $$A[i]$$ with $$A[j]$$
        \ENDIF
        \STATE exchange $$A[i]$$ with $$A[r]$$
    \ENDFOR
\ENDPROCEDURE
\end{algorithmic}
\end{algorithm}</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Generates:</p> <pre><code class="language-pseudocode">% This quicksort algorithm is extracted from Chapter 7, Introduction to Algorithms (3rd edition)
\begin{algorithm}
\caption{Quicksort}
\begin{algorithmic}
\PROCEDURE{Quicksort}{$$A, p, r$$}
    \IF{$$p &lt; r$$}
        \STATE $$q = $$ \CALL{Partition}{$$A, p, r$$}
        \STATE \CALL{Quicksort}{$$A, p, q - 1$$}
        \STATE \CALL{Quicksort}{$$A, q + 1, r$$}
    \ENDIF
\ENDPROCEDURE
\PROCEDURE{Partition}{$$A, p, r$$}
    \STATE $$x = A[r]$$
    \STATE $$i = p - 1$$
    \FOR{$$j = p$$ \TO $$r - 1$$}
        \IF{$$A[j] &lt; x$$}
            \STATE $$i = i + 1$$
            \STATE exchange
            $$A[i]$$ with $$A[j]$$
        \ENDIF
        \STATE exchange $$A[i]$$ with $$A[r]$$
    \ENDFOR
\ENDPROCEDURE
\end{algorithmic}
\end{algorithm}
</code></pre>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included pseudo code could look like]]></summary></entry></feed>